José Jair Santanna

Ph.D. Researcher, Lecturer, Network Security Specialist & (Big) Data Analyst

Contact

Drienerlolaan 5, Zilverling 5110, 7522 NB Enschede, The Netherlands.

+31 (6) 42330703

http://jairsantanna.com j.i.santanna@utwente.nl

Languages

portuguese native english fluency spanish comprehension dutch comprehension

Programming

Bash, Python, C#,SQL PIG, Spark & Impala

Professional Objective

I am currently a PhD candidate at University of Twente (ending in 2017) in a awesome research group called DACS. My research is founded by an European project focus in network of Excellence, called Flamingo, and funded by the Netherlands Organisation for Scientific Research in a project called D3.

I am interested in a research & development position with focus on network security and the use of big data technologies to improve network data analysis. A position where I can transfer my enthusiasm, knowledge, skills and experience into meaningful innovation that improve the security in computer networks, specially in the Internet.

Education

2013–Now **Doctor** in Computer Science University of Twente, The Netherlands

"The DDoS as a \$ervice Phenomenon". Supervisor: Prof. dr. ir. Aiko Pras

2010–2012 **Master** in Computer Science Federal University of Rio Grande do Sul, Brazil

"A BPM-based Solution for Inter-domain Circuit Management". The outcome of this work generated a product still in use by the Brazilian National Education and Research Network (RNP) (Link: http://meican.cipo.rnp.br/).

Supervisor: Prof. dr. Lisandro Zambenedetti Granville

Supervisor. From all Lisariaro Zambonedetti Granvillo

2005–2010 **Bachelor** in Computer Engineer Federal University of Pará, Brazil

"A Comparative Evaluation of DCCP Protocol in a Experimental Mesh Network."

Supervisor: Dr. Kelvin Lopes Dias

Experience

Technical Adviser

2016 To the Yokohama National University Japan

For the production of a report on "Reflection & Amplification DDoS attacks" requested by the *Japanese Ministry of Internal Affairs and Communications*.

2016 To the Dutch National Cyber Security Center and the Scientific Research & Documen-

tation Center The Netherlands

For the production of a report on "Cyber metrics 2016: DDoS and Malware"

requested by the Dutch Ministry of Security and Justice.

Assistant Professor

2012–2013 University of Santa Cruz do Sul (UNISC)

Santa Cruz do Sul, Brazil

Tasks & Responsibilities: Supervise students and teach the following courses: Computer Networks, Computer Network Management, and Digital Systems.

Guest Lecturer

2015 & 2016 **Product Design to Online Business (course)** University of Twente, The Netherlands

Audience: bachelor students of industrial engineering and business information

technology.

2015 **Network Security (course)** University of Twente, The Netherlands

Audience: master and bachelor students of computer science, electrical engineer, and telematics from the University of Twente, 3TU cyber security, and

members of ICT labs.

2015 Cybercrime & Cybersecurity (minor) University of Twente, The Netherlands

Audience: bachelor students from University of Twente, European Research Center for Information (ERCIS), Westfälische Wilhelms - Univerität Münster, Uni-

versität Innsbruck, and University of Leicester.

Software Developer

2015-Now Distributed Denial of Service Attacks Database (DDoSDB)

Link: http://bit.ly/ddos_db

An initiative to develop the largest open database with DDoS attacks.

Languages: Python, Bash, Pig Latin & Apache Impala

2010–2011 Management Environment of Inter-domain Circuits for Advanced Networks (MEICAN)

Link: http://meican.cipo.rnp.br/

Development of an Executable Network Management Policies Editor sponsored

by the Brazilian National Education and Research Network (RNP).

Language: WS-BPEL

2009 Support for Planning Sustainable Electrical Power Generation via Vegetable Oil.

Desktop application part of a Ph.D. thesis (chapter 5 and 6) sponsored by

Eletronorte, subsidiary of the major Brazilian power utility (Eletrobrás).

Language: C#.Net & mySQL

Student Supervisor

[M.Sc. Degree] Joey de Vries [Cum Laude], Justyna Chromik [Cum Laude], Wouter de Vries, Mark Wierbosch, and Jarmo van Lenthe.

[B.Sc. Degree] Roeland Krak, Max Kerkers, Dirk Maan, Jochum Börger, and Guilherme Dressler.

International Conference Reviewer

IFIP Networking (2014–2016), IEEE/IFIP Network Operations and Management Symposium (2014 & 2016), Asia-Pacific Network Operations and Management Symposium (2013 & 2014), IFIP/IEEE Integrated Management (2015), International Conference on Autonomous Infrastructure, Management and Security (2015), International Conference on Network and Service Management (2013–2015), EUNICE Conference (2013) & IEEE Symposium on Computers and Communications (2011).

Awards

2015	Best Ph.D. 'Elevator Pitch'	(1 st Place)	CTIT Symposium, University of Twente
2015	Best Poster (3 rd Place)		CTIT Symposium, University of Twente
2015	Best Paper Award	Autonomous Infrastructure,	Management and Security Conference
2015	Top Papers Nomination Bra	zilian Symposium on Comp	uter Networks and Distributed Systems
2010	Student Award (3 rd Place)	Computer En	gineer, Federal University of Pará, Brazil

Presentations

More than 30 presentations in the last 3 years (available on my slideshare.net/jjcsantanna), among those I highlight:

2015	Oral Presentation	at Logius (part of the Dutch Ministry of the Interior and Kingdom Relations).
2015	Oral Presentation	to the Dutch National Management Organization of Internet Providers (NBIP).
2015	Oral Presentation	to the Dutch National Cyber Security Centrum (NCSC).
2013 & 2015	Oral Presentation	at the 31^{th} and 36^{th} IRTF Network Management Research Group (NMRG).

Scientific Appendix

Description of Ph.D. Research

Publications